<?xml version="1,0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
  <text>
<title><note type="editorial" rend="italics">The Quickest Runners.</note></title>
<body>
<p>There was a large reward offered--indeed, there were two rewards
offered, a larger and a lesser one--for the greatest speed, not in one
race alone, but to such as had got on fastest throughout the year.</p>

<p>"I got the highest prize," said <character name="the hare">the hare</character>. "One had a right to expect
justice when one's own family and best friends were in the council;
but that <character name="the snail">the snail</character> should have got the second prize I consider as
almost an insult to me."</p>

<p>"No," observed <character name="the wooden fence">the wooden fence</character>, which had been a witness to the
distribution of the prizes; "you must take diligence and good will
into consideration. That remark was made by several very estimable
persons, and that was also my opinion. To be sure <character name="the snail">the snail</character> took half
a year to cross the threshold; but he broke his thigh-bone in the
tremendous exertion which that was for him. He devoted himself
entirely to this race; and, moreover, he ran with his house on his
back. All these weighed in his favour, and so he obtained the second
prize."</p>

<p>"I think my claims might also have been taken into consideration,"
said <character name="the swallow">the swallow</character>. More speedy than I, in flight and motion, I believe
no one has shown himself. And where have I not been? Far, far away!"</p>

<p>"And that is just your misfortune," said <character name="the wooden fence"> the wooden fence</character>. "You gad
about too much. You are always on the wing, ready to start out of the
country when it begins to freeze. You have no love for your
fatherland. You cannot claim any consideration in it."</p>

<p>"But if I were to sleep all the winter through on the moor," inquired
<character name="the swallow">the swallow</character>--"sleep my whole time away--should I be thus entitled to
be taken into consideration?"</p>

<p>"Obtain an affidavit from the old woman of the moor that you did sleep
half the year in your fatherland, then your claims will be taken into
consideration."</p>

<p>"I deserved the first prize instead of the second," said <character name="the snail">the snail</character>. "I
know very well that <character name="the hare">the hare </character>only ran from cowardice, whenever he
thought there was danger near. I, on the contrary, made the trial the
business of my life, and I have become a cripple in consequence of my
exertions. If any one had a right to the first prize it was I; but I
make no fuss; I scorn to do so."</p>

<p>"I can declare upon my honour that each prize, at least as far as my
voice in the matter went, was accorded with strict justice," said <character name="the old sign-post in the wood">the
old sign-post in the wood</character>, who had been one of the arbitrators. "I
always act with due reflection, and according to order. Seven times
before have I had the honour to be engaged in the distribution of the
prizes, but never until to-day have I had my own way carried out. My
plan has always hitherto been thwarted--that was, to give the first
prize to one of the first letters in the alphabet, and the second
prize to one of the last letters. If you will be so good as to grant
me your attention, I will explain it to you. The eighth letter in the
alphabet from <note type="editorial" rend="italics">A</note> is <note type="editorial" rend="italics">H</note>--that stands for <note type="editorial" rend="italics">Hare</note>, and therefore I
awarded the greatest prize to the Hare; and the eighth letter from the
end is <note type="editorial" rend="italics">S</note>, therefore the <note type="editorial" rend="italics">Snail</note> obtained the second prize. Next time
the <note type="editorial" rend="italics">I</note> will carry off the first prize, and <note type="editorial" rend="italics">R</note> the second. A due
attention to order and rotation should prevail in all rewards and
appointments. Everything should go according to rule. <note type="editorial" rend="italics">Rule</note> must
precede merit."</p>

<p>"I should certainly have voted for myself, had I not been among the
judges," said <character name="the mule">the mule</character>. "People must take into account not only how
quickly one goes, but what other circumstances are in question; as,
for instance, how much one carries. But I would not this time have
thought about that, neither about <character name="the hare">the hare's</character> wisdom in his flight--his
tact in springing suddenly to one side, to put <character name="the hare">his</character> pursuers on the
wrong scent, away from his place of concealment. No; there is one
thing many people think much of, and which ought never to be
disregarded. It is called THE BEAUTIFUL. I saw that in <character name="the hare">the hare's</character>
charming well-grown ears; it is quite a pleasure to see how long they
are. I fancied that I beheld myself when I was little, and so I voted
for him."</p>

<p>"Hush!" said <character name="the fly">the fly</character>. "As for me, I will not speak; I will only say
one word. I know right well that I have outrun more than one hare. The
other day I broke the hind legs of one of the young ones. I was
sitting on the locomotive before the train: I often do that. One sees
so well there one's own speed. A young hare ran for a long time in
front of the engine: he had no idea that I was there. At length he was
just going to turn off the line, when the locomotive went over his
hind legs and broke them, for I was sitting on it. The hare remained
lying there, but I drove on. That was surely getting before him; but I
do not care for the prize."</p>

<p>"It appears to me," thought <character name="the wild rose">the wild rose</character>, but she did not say it--it
is not her nature to express her ideas openly, though it might have
been well had she done so--"it appears to me that <character name="the sunbeam">the sunbeam</character> should
have had the first prize of honour, and the second also. It passes in
a moment the immeasurable space from the sun down to us, and comes
with such power that all nature is awakened by it. It has such beauty,
that all we roses redden and become fragrant under it. The high
presiding authorities do not seem to have noticed _it_ at all. Were I
<character name="the sunbeam">the sunbeam</character>, I would give each of them a sunstroke, that I would; but
it would only make them crazy, and they will very likely be that
without it. I shall say nothing," thought the wild rose. "There is
peace in the wood; it is delightful to blossom, to shed refreshing
perfume around, to live amidst the songs of birds and the rustling of
trees; but the sun's rays will outlive us all."</p>

<p>"What is the first prize?" asked <character name="the earth-worm">the earth-worm</character>, who had overslept
himself, and only now joined them.</p>

<p>"It gives free entrance to the kitchen garden," said <character name="the mule">the mule</character>. "I
proposed the prize, as a clear-sighted and judicious member of the
meeting, with a view to <character name="the hare">the hare's</character> advantage. I was resolved he should
have it, and he is now provided for. <character name="the snail">The snail</character> has permission to sit
on the stone fence, and to enjoy the moss and the sunshine; and,
moreover, he is appointed to be one of the chief judges of the next
race. It is well to have one who is practically acquainted with the
business in hand--on a committee, as human beings call it. I must say
I expect great things from the future--we have made so good a
beginning."</p>




<title><note type="editorial" rend="italics">The Bell's Hollow.</note></title>


<p>"Ding-dong! ding-dong!" sounded from <character name="the bell">the buried bell</character> in <place type="body of water" name= "Odense river">Odensee river.</place>
What sort of a river is that? Every child in the town of <place type="city" name="Odense">Odensee</place> knows
it. It flows round the foot of the gardens, from the locks to the
water-mill, away under the wooden bridges. In the river grow yellow
water-lilies, brown feather-like reeds, and the soft velvet-like
bulrushes, so high and so large. Old, split willow trees, bent and
twisted, hang far over the water by the side of the monks' meadows and
the bleaching greens; but a little above is garden after garden--the
one very different from the other; some with beautiful flowers and
arbours, clean and in prim array, like dolls' villages; some only
filled with cabbages; while in others there are no attempts at a
garden to be seen at all, only great elder trees stretching themselves
out, and hanging over the running water, which here and there is
deeper than an oar can fathom.</p>

<p>Opposite to the nunnery is the deepest part. It is called "The Bell's
Hollow," and there dwells <character name="the merman">the merman</character>. <character name="the merman">He</character> sleeps by day when the sun
shines through the water, but comes forth on the clear starry nights,
and by moonlight. He is very old. Grandmothers have heard of him from
their grandmothers. They said he lived a lonely life, and had scarcely
any one to speak to except <character name="the bell">the large old church bell</character>. Once upon a time
it hung up in the steeple of the church; but now there is no trace
either of the steeple or the church, which was then called <place type="church" name="Saint Albani">Saint
Albani</place>.</p>

<p>"Ding-dong! ding-dong!" rang <character name="the bell">the bell</character> while it stood in the steeple;
and one evening when the sun was setting, and <character name="the bell">the bell</character> was in full
motion, it broke loose, and flew through the air, its shining metal
glowing in the red sunbeams. "Ding-dong! ding-dong! now I am going to
rest," sang <character name="the bell">the bell</character>; and it flew out to Odensee river, where it was
deepest, and therefore that spot is now called "The Bell's Hollow."
But it found neither sleep nor rest there. Down at <character name="the merman">the merman's</character> it
still rings; so that at times it is heard above, through the water,
and many people say that its tones foretell a death; but there is no
truth in that, for it rings to amuse <character name="the merman">the merman</character>, who is now no longer
alone.</p>

<p>And what does <character name="the bell">the bell</character> relate? It was so very old, it was there before
our grandmothers' grandmothers were born, and yet it was a child
compared with <character name="the merman">the merman</character>, who is an old, quiet, strange-looking
person, with eel-skin leggings, a scaly tunic adorned with yellow
water-lilies, a wreath of sedges in his hair, and weeds in his beard.
It must be confessed he was not very handsome to look at.</p>

<p>It would take a year and a day to repeat all that <character name="the bell">the bell</character> said, for
it told the same old stories over and over again very minutely, making
them sometimes longer, sometimes shorter, according to its mood. It
told of the olden days--the rigorous, dark times.</p>

<p>To the tower upon St. Albani Church, where <character name="the bell">the bell</character> hung, ascended <character name="the monk">a
monk</character>. He was both young and handsome, but had an air of deep
melancholy. He looked through an aperture out over the Odensee river.
Its bed then was broad, and the monks' meadows were a lake. He gazed
over them, and over the green mound called "The Nuns Hill," beyond
which the cloister lay, where the light shone from a nun's cell. He
had known her well, and he remembered the past, and his heart beat
wildly at the recollection.</p>

<p>"Ding-dong! ding-dong!" This was one of <character name="the bell">the bell's</character> stories:--</p>

<p>"There came up to the tower one day an idiot servant of the bishop;
and when <character name="the bell">I, the bell</character>, who am cast in hard and heavy metal, swung about
and pealed, I could have broken his head, for he seated himself
immediately under me, and began to play with two sticks, exactly as if
it had been a stringed instrument, and he sang to it thus: 'Now I may
venture to sing aloud what elsewhere I dare not whisper--sing of all
that is kept hidden behind locks and bolts. Yonder it is cold and
damp. The rats eat the living bodies. No one knows of it; no one hears
of it--not even now, when <character name="the bell">the bell</character> is pouring forth its loudest
peal--ding-dong! ding-dong!'</p>

<p>"There was a <character name="King Knud">king</character>: he was called Knud. He humbled himself both before
bishops and monks; but as he unjustly oppressed the people, and laid
heavy taxes on them, they armed themselves with all sorts of weapons,
and chased him away as if he had been a wild beast. He sought shelter
in the church, and had the doors and windows closed. The furious
multitude surrounded the sacred edifice, as I heard related; the
crows and the ravens, and the jackdaws to boot, became scared by the
noise and the tumult; they flew up into the tower, and out again; they
looked on the multitude below, they looked also in at the church
windows, and shrieked out what they saw.</p>

<p>"<character name="King Knud">King Knud</character> knelt before the altar and prayed; his brothers Erik and
Benedict stood guarding him with their drawn swords; but the king's
servitor, the false Blake, betrayed his lord. They knew outside where
he could be reached. A stone was cast in through the window at him,
and the <character name="King Knud">king</character> lay dead. There were shouts and cries among the angry
crowd, and cries among the flocks of frightened birds; and I joined
them too. I pealed forth, 'Ding-dong! ding-dong!'</p>

<p>"<character name="the bell">The church bell</character> hangs high, sees far around, receives visits from
birds, and understands their language. To it whispers the wind through
the wickets and apertures, and through every little chink; and the
wind knows everything. He hears it from the air, for it encompasses
all living things; it even enters into the lungs of human beings--it
hears every word and every sigh. The air knows all, the wind repeats
all, and <character name="the bell">the bell</character> understands their speech, and rings it forth to the
whole world--'Ding dong! ding dong!'</p>

<p>"But all this was too much for me to hear and to know. I had not
strength enough to ring it all out. I became so wearied, so heavy,
that the beam from which I hung broke, and I flew through the luminous
air down to where the river is deepest, where <character name="the merman">the merman</character> dwells alone
in solitude; and here I am, year after year, relating to him what I
have seen and what I have heard. 'Ding-dong! ding-dong!'"</p>

<p>Thus rang the chimes from "The Bell's Hollow" in the Odensee river, as
my grandmother declares.</p>

<p>But our schoolmaster says there is no <character name="the bell">bell</character> ringing down there, for it
could not be; and there is no <character name="the merman">merman</character> down there, for there are no
mermen; and, when all the church bells are ringing loudly, he says
that it is not the bells, but the air that makes the sound. My
grandmother told me that <character name="the bell">the bell</character> also said this; so, since the
schoolmaster and <character name="the bell">the bell</character> agree in this, no doubt it is true.</p>

<p>The air knows everything. It is round us, it is in us; it speaks of
our thoughts and our actions; and it proclaims them farther than did
<character name="the bell">the bell</character> now down in the Hollow in Odensee river, where <character name="the merman">the merman</character>
dwells--it proclaims all out into the great vault of heaven, far, far
away, even into eternity, up to where the glorious bells of paradise
peal in tones unknown to mortal ears.</p>




<title><note type="editorial" rend="italics">Soup made of a Sausage-stick.</note></title>


<subheading>I.</subheading>

<p>"We had a capital dinner yesterday," said an <character name="aged female mouse">aged female mouse</character> to one
who had not been at the feast. "I sat only twenty-one from the old
<character name="King of Mice">King of the Mice</character>: that was not being badly placed. Shall I tell you
what we had for dinner? It was all very well arranged. We had mouldy
bread, the skin of bacon, tallow candles, and sausages. Twice we
returned to the charge: it was as good as if we had had two dinners.
There was nothing but good-humour and pleasant chit-chat, as in an
agreeable family circle. Not a mite was left except the sausage-stick.
The conversation happened to fall upon the possibility of making soup
of a sausage-stick. All said they had heard of it, but no one had ever
tasted that soup, or knew how to prepare it. A health was proposed to
the inventor, who, it was remarked, deserved to be superintendent of
the poor. Was not that witty? And the old <character name="King of Mice">King of the Mice</character> arose and
declared that the one among the young mice who could prepare the soup
in question most palatably should be his queen, and he would grant
them a year and a day for the trial."</p>

<p>"Well, that was not a bad idea," said the other mouse. "But how is the
soup made?"</p>

<p>"Ay, how is it made? That was what they were all asking, the young and
the old. Every one was willing enough to become the queen, but they
were all loath to take the trouble of going out into the world to
acquire the prescribed qualification; yet it was absolutely necessary
to do so. But it does not suit every one to leave her family and her
snug old mouse-hole. One cannot be going out every day after cheese
parings, and sniffing the rind of bacon. No: such pursuits, too often
indulged in, would perchance put them in the way of being eaten alive
by a cat."</p>

<p>These apprehensions were quite terrible enough to scare most of the
mice from going forth upon the search of knowledge. Only four
presented themselves for the undertaking. They were young and active,
but very poor. They would have gone to the four corners of the earth,
if only good fortune might attend their enterprise. Each of them took
with her a sausage-stick to remind her what she was travelling for. It
was to be her walking staff.</p>

<p>On the 1st of May they set out, and on the 1st of May, a year after,
they returned; but only three of them. The fourth did not report
herself, and sent no tidings of herself; and yet it was the day fixed
for the royal decision.</p>

<p>"There shall be no sadness or no drawback to our pleasure," said the
<character name="King of Mice">King of the Mice</character>, as he gave orders that every mouse within several
miles round should be invited. They were to assemble in the kitchen.
The three travelled mice were drawn up in a row alone. In the place
of the fourth, who was absent, was deposited a sausage-stick covered
with black crepe. No one ventured to utter a word until the three had
made their statements, and <character name="King of Mice">the king</character> had determined what more was to be
said.</p>

<p>We have now to hear all this.</p>


<subheading>II.

WHAT THE <character name="first little mouse">FIRST LITTLE MOUSE</character> HAD SEEN AND LEARNT ON HER JOURNEY.</subheading>

<p>"When I first went forth into the wide world," said the <character name="first little mouse">little mouse</character>,
"I thought, as so many of my age do, that I had swallowed all the
wisdom of the earth; but that was not the case--it required a year and
a day for that to come to pass. I went at once to sea, on board a ship
which was bound for the north. I had heard that cooks at sea were
pretty well acquainted with their business; but there is little to do
when one has plenty of sides of bacon, barrels of salt meat, and musty
meal at hand. One lives delicately on these nice things; but one
learns nothing like making soup of a sausage-stick. We sailed for many
days and nights, and a stormy and wet time we had of it. When we
reached our destination I left the vessel: this was far away up in the
north.</p>

<p>"One has a strange feeling on leaving one's own mouse-hole at home,
being carried away in a ship, which becomes a home for the time, and
suddenly finding one's self, at the distance of more than a hundred
miles, standing alone in a foreign land. I saw myself amidst a large
tangled wood full of pine and birch trees. Their scent was so strong!
It is not at all my taste; but the perfume from the wild plants was so
spicy that I was quite charmed, and thought of the sausage and the
seasoning for the soup. There were lakes amidst the forest, the water
was beautifully clear close at hand, but looking in the distance as
black as ink. There were white swans upon the lake. I mistook them at
first for foam, they lay so still; but when I saw them fly I
recognised them. They, however, belong to the race of geese. No one
can deny his kindred. I like mine, and I hastened to seek the field
mice, who, truth to tell, know very little except what concerns their
food; and it was just that on account of which I had travelled to a
foreign country. That any one should think of making soup out of a
sausage-stick seemed to them so extraordinary an idea, that it was
speedily circulated through the whole wood; but that the problem
should be solved they considered an impossibility. Little did I think
then that the very same night I should be initiated into the process.</p>

<p>"It was midsummer; therefore it was that the woods scented so
strongly, they said; therefore were the plants so aromatic in their
perfume, the lake so clear, and yet so dark with the white swans upon
them. On the borders of the forest, amidst three or four houses, was
erected a pole as high as a mainmast, and around it hung wreaths and
ribbons. This was the Maypole. Girls and young men danced round it,
and sang to the accompaniment of the fiddler's violin. All went on
merrily till after the sun had set, and the moon had risen, but I took
no part in the festivity; for what had a little mouse to do with a
forest ball? I sat down amidst the soft moss, and held fast my
sausage-stick. The moon shone brightly on a place where there was a
solitary tree surrounded by moss so fine--yes, I venture to say as
fine as the Mice-King's skin--but it had a green tint, and its colour
was very soothing to the eye. All at once I saw approaching a set of
the most beautiful little people, so little that they would only have
reached to my knee; they looked like men and women, but they were
better proportioned. They called themselves Elves, and their garments
were composed of the leaves of flowers, trimmed with the wings of
gnats and flies--not at all ugly. They seemed as if they were
searching for something--what I did not know; but when they came a
little nearer to me their leader tapped my sausage-stick, and said,
'This is what we want; it is all ready, all prepared;' and he became
more and more joyful as he gazed upon my walking-stick.</p>

<p>"'You may borrow it, but not keep it,' said I.</p>

<p>"'Not keep it!' they all exclaimed together, as they seized my
sausage-stick, and, dancing away to the green mossy spot, placed the
sausage-stick there in the centre of it. They determined also on
having a Maypole; and the stick they had just captured seeming quite
suited to their purpose, it was soon ornamented.</p>

<p>"Small spiders spun gold threads around it--hung up waving veils and
flags so finely worked, shining so snow-white under the moonbeams,
that my eyes were quite dazzled. They took the colours from the wings
of the butterflies, and sprinkled them on the white webs, till they
seemed to be laden with flowers and diamonds. I did not know my own
sausage-stick--it had become such a magnificent Maypole, that
certainly had not its equal in the world. And now came tripping
forwards the great mass of the elves, most of them very slightly
clad; but what they did wear was of the finest materials. I looked
on, of course, but in the background, for I was too big for them.</p>

<p>"Then what a game commenced! It was as if a thousand glass bells were
ringing, the sound was so clear and full. I fancied the swans were
singing, and I also thought I heard cuckoos and thrushes. At length it
seemed as if the whole wood was filled with music. There were the
sweet voices of children, the ringing of bells, and the songs of
birds; and all these melodious sounds seemed to proceed from the
elves' Maypole--an orchestra in itself--and that was my sausage-stick.
I never would have believed that so much could have come from it; but
much, of course, depended on what hands it fell into. I became very
much agitated, and I wept, as a little mouse can weep, from sheer
pleasure.</p>

<p>"The night was all too short; but, at this time of the year, the
nights are not long up yonder. At the dawn of day there arose a fresh
breeze; the surface of the lake became ruffled; all the delicately
fine veils and flags disappeared in the air; the swinging kiosks of
cobwebs, the suspension bridges and balustrades, or whatever they are
called, which were constructed from leaf to leaf, vanished into
nothing; six elves brought me my sausage-stick, and at the same time
asked if I had any wish they could fulfil; whereupon I begged them to
tell me how soup could be made from a sausage-stick.</p>

<p>"'What we can do,' said the foremost, laughing, 'you have just seen.
You could scarcely have recognised your sausage-stick.'</p>

<p>"'You mean as you transformed it,' said I; and then I told them the
cause of my journey, and what was expected at home from it. 'Of what
use,' I asked, 'will it be to the King of the Mice and all our large
community that I have seen this beautiful sight? I cannot shake the
sausage-stick and say, You see here the stick--now comes the soup!
That would be like a hoax.'</p>

<p>"Then the elf dipped its little finger into a blue violet, and said to
me,--</p>

<p>"'Look! I spread a charm over your walking-stick, and when you return
to the palace of the King of the Mice make it touch the king's warm
breast, and violets will spring from every part of the staff, even in
the coldest winter weather. See! you have now something worth taking
home, and perhaps a little more.'"</p>

<p>But before the little mouse had finished repeating what the elf had
said she laid her staff against the king's breast, and sure enough
there sprang forth from it the loveliest flowers. They yielded so
strong a perfume that the king commanded that the mice who stood
nearest the chimney should stick their tails in the fire, in order
that the smell of the singed hair should overpower the odour from the
flowers, which was very offensive.</p>

<p>"But what was 'the little more' you spoke of?" asked the <character name="King of Mice">King of the
Mice</character>.</p>

<p>"Oh!" said the <character name="first little mouse">little mouse</character>, "it is what is called an _effect_;" and
so she turned her sausage-stick. And behold, there were no more
flowers visible! She held only the naked stick, and she moved it like
a stick for beating time.</p>

<p>"The violets are for sight, smell, and touch, the elf told me; but
there are still wanting hearing and taste."</p>

<p>She beat time, and there was music--not such, however, as sounded in
the wood at the elfin fête; no, such as is heard at times in the
kitchen. It came suddenly, like the wind whistling down the chimney.
The pots and the pans boiled over, and the shovel thundered against
the large brass kettle. It stopped as suddenly as it had commenced;
and then was only to be heard the smothered song of the tea-kettle,
which was so strange with its tones rising and falling, and the little
pot and the large pot boiling, the one not troubling itself about the
other, as if neither could think. Then the little mouse moved her
time-stick faster and faster; the pots bubbled up and boiled over; the
wind roared in the chimney; the commotion was so great that the little
mouse herself got frightened, and dropped the stick.</p>

<p>"It was hard work to make that soup," cried the <character name="King of Mice">old king</character>; "but where
is the result--the dish?"</p>

<p>"That is all," said the <character name="first little mouse">little mouse</character>, courtesying.</p>

<p>"All! Then let us hear what the next has to tell," said the <character name="King of Mice">king</character>.</p>


<subheading>III.

WHAT <character name="the second mouse">THE SECOND MOUSE</character> HAD TO RELATE.</subheading>

<p>"I was born in the palace library," said the <character name="the second mouse">second mouse</character>. "I, and
several members of my family there, have never had the good fortune to
enter the dining-room, let alone the pantry. It was only when I first
began my travels, and now again to-day, that I have even beheld a
kitchen. We had often to endure hunger in the library, but we acquired
much knowledge. The report of the reward offered by royalty for the
discovery of the process by which soup could be made of a
sausage-stick reached us even up there, and my grandmother thereupon
looked for a manuscript which, though she could not read herself, she
had heard read, wherein it was said,--</p>

<p>"'A poet can make soup out of a sausage-stick.'</p>

<p>"She asked me if I were a poet. I confessed I was not, to which she
replied that I must go and try to become one. I begged to know what
was to be done to acquire this art, for it appeared to me about as
difficult to attain as to make the soup itself. But my grandmother had
heard a good deal of reading, and she told me that the three things
principally necessary were--good sense, imagination, and feeling. 'If
thou canst go and furnish thyself with _these_, thou wilt be a poet;
and there will be every chance of thy success in the matter of the
sausage-stick.'</p>

<p>"So I set off to the westward, out into the wide world, to become a
poet.</p>

<p>"_Good sense_ I knew was the most important of all things, the two
other qualities not being so highly esteemed. So I went first after
good sense. Well, where did it dwell? 'Go to the ant; consider her
ways, and be wise,' a great king of the Hebrews has said. I knew this
from the library, and I never stopped until I reached a large
ant-hill; and there I settled myself to watch them.</p>

<p>"They are a very respectable tribe, the ants, and full of good sense;
everything among them is as correctly done as a well-calculated sum in
arithmetic. 'To labour and to lay eggs,' say they, 'is to live in the
present, and to provide for the future;' and that they assuredly do.
They divide themselves into the clean ants and the dirty ones. Rank is
distinguished by a number. The queen ant is number one, and her will
is their only law. She has swallowed all the wisdom, and it was of
consequence to me to listen to her; but she said so much and was so
profoundly wise, that I could scarcely comprehend her.</p>

<p>"She said that their hill was the highest in the world; but close to
the hill stood a tree that was higher, certainly much higher. She
could not deny this, so she did not allude to it. One evening an ant
had lost his way, and finding himself on the tree, he crept up the
trunk, not as far as the top, but much higher than any ant had ever
gone before; and when he descended, and found his way home at last, he
imprudently told in the ant-hill of something much higher at a little
distance from it. This was taken by one and all as an affront to the
whole community, and the offending ant was condemned to have his mouth
muzzled, as well as to perpetual solitude. But shortly after another
ant got as far as the tree, and made a similar journey and a similar
discovery. He spoke of it, however, discreetly and mysteriously, and
as he happened to be an ant of consideration--one of the clean--they
believed him; and when he died they placed an egg-shell over him as a
monument in honour of his extensive knowledge.</p>

<p>"I observed," said the <character name="the second mouse">little mouse</character>, "that the ants continually move
with their eggs on their backs. One of them dropped hers. She tried
very hard to get it up again, but could not succeed; then two others
came and helped her with all their might, until they had nearly lost
their own eggs, whereupon they let the attempt alone, for one is
nearest to one's self; and the queen ant remarked that both heart and
good sense had been shown. 'These two qualities place us ants among
reasonable beings,' she said. 'Sense ought to be, and is, of the most
consequence; and I have the most of that;' and she raised herself, in
her self-satisfaction, on her hind leg. I could not mistake her, and
I swallowed her. 'Go to the ant; consider her ways, and be wise.' I
had now the queen.</p>

<p>"I then went nearer to the above-mentioned large tree: it was an oak.
It had high branches, a majestic crown of leaves, and was very old. I
perceived that a living creature resided in it--a female. She was
called a Dryad. She had been born with the tree, and would die with
it. I had heard of this in the library; and now I beheld one of the
real trees, and a real oak-nymph. She uttered a frightful shriek when
she saw me near her; for she was like all women, very much afraid of
mice. She, however, had more reason to be afraid of me than others of
her sex have, for I could have gnawed the tree in two, and on it hung
her life. I spoke to her kindly and cordially. This gave her courage,
and she took me in her slender hand; and when she understood what had
brought me out into the wide world, she promised that I should,
perhaps that very night, become possessed of one of the two treasures
of which I was in search. She told me that Imagination was her very
particular friend; that he was as charming as the God of Love; and
that he often, for many an hour, sought repose under the spreading
foliage of the tree, which then sighed more musically over the two. He
called her _his_ dryad, she said, and the tree _his_ tree. The mighty,
gnarled, majestic oak was just to his taste, with its broad roots sunk
deep into the earth, its trunk and its coronal rising so high in the
free air, meeting the drifting snow, the cutting winds, and the bright
sunshine, before they had reached the ground. All this she said, and
she continued: 'The birds sing up yonder, and tell of foreign lands,
and upon the only decayed branch the stork has built a nest; and it
is a pleasure to hear of the country where the pyramids stand. All
this Fancy can well depict, and very much more. I myself can describe
life in the woods from the time that I was quite little, and this tree
was so tiny that a nettle could have covered it, until now, when it is
so strong and mighty. Sit down yonder under the woodruffs, and be on
the look-out. When Fancy comes I shall find an opportunity of pinching
his wing, and stealing a little feather from it. You shall take that,
and no poet will ever have been better provided. Will that do?'</p>

<p>"And Imagination came; a feather was plucked from him, and I got it,"
said the little mouse. "I held it in the water till it became soft. It
was still hard of digestion, but I managed to gnaw it all up. It is
not at all easy to stuff one's self so as to be a poet--there is so
much to be put in one. I had now got two of the ingredients--good
sense and imagination; and I knew by their help that the third
ingredient was to be found in the library; for a great man has said
and written that there are romances which are useful in easing people
of a superfluity of tears, and which also act as a sort of swamp to
cast feelings into. I remembered some of these books; they had always
looked very enticing to me. They were so thumbed, so greasy, they must
have been very popular.</p>

<p>"I returned home to the library, ate almost as much as a whole
romance--that is to say, the soft part of it, the pith--but the crust,
the binding, I let alone. When I had digested this, and another to
boot, I perceived how my inside was stirred up; so I ate part of a
third, and then I considered myself a poet, and every one about me
said I was. I had headaches, of course, and all sorts of aches. I
thought over what story I could work up about a sausage-stick, and
there was no end of sticks and pegs crowding my mind. The queen ant
had had an uncommon intellect. I remembered the man who took a white
peg into his mouth, and both he and it became invisible. All my
thoughts ran upon sticks. A poet can write even upon these; and I am a
poet I trust, for I have fagged hard to be one. I shall be able every
day in the week to amuse you with the story of a stick. This is my
soup."</p>

<p>"Let us hear the third," said the <character name="King of Mice">King of the Mice</character>.</p>

<p>"Pip, pip!" said a <character name="the fourth mouse">little mouse</character> at the kitchen door. It was the fourth
of them, the one they thought dead. She tripped in, and jumped upon
the upper end of the sausage-stick with the black crape. She had been
journeying day and night, travelling on the railroad by the goods
train, in which she took great pleasure, and yet she had almost
arrived too late; but she hurried forward, puffing and panting, and
looking very much jaded. She had lost her sausage-stick, but not her
voice; for she began talking with the utmost velocity, as if every one
was dying to hear her, and no one could say anything to the purpose
but herself. How she did chatter! But she had arrived so unexpectedly
that no one had time to find fault with her or her talking, so she
went on. Now let us listen.</p>


<subheading>IV.

WHAT THE <character name="the fourth mouse">FOURTH MOUSE</character>--WHO SPOKE BEFORE THE THIRD ONE HAD SPOKEN--HAD
TO RELATE.</subheading>

<p>"I went straight to the greatest city," she said. "I do not remember
its name. I do not recollect names well. I came from the railway with
confiscated goods to the town council-hall, and there I ran to the
jailer. He spoke of his prisoners, especially of one of them, who had
uttered some very imprudent words; and when these had been repeated,
and written down and read, 'The whole,' said he, 'was only--soup of a
sausage-stick; but that soup may cost him dear.' I felt interested in
the prisoner," continued the little mouse, "and I watched for an
opportunity to go in where he was. There is always a mouse-hole behind
locked doors. He looked very pale, had a dark beard, and large shining
eyes. The lamp smoked; but the walls were accustomed to this. They did
not turn any blacker. The prisoner was scratching on them both
pictures and verses; but I did not read the latter. I fancy he was
tired of being alone, for I was a welcome guest. He enticed me with
crumbs of bread, with his flute, and kind words. He was so happy with
me! I put confidence in him, and we became friends. He shared with me
bread and water, and gave me cheese and sausages. I lived luxuriously;
but it was not alone the good cheer that detained me. He allowed me to
run upon his hand and arm all the way up to his shoulder; he allowed
me to creep into his beard, and called me his little friend. I became
very dear to him, and our regard was mutual. I forgot my errand out in
the wide world; I forgot my sausage-stick in a crevice in the floor;
and there it still lies. I wished to remain where I was; for, if I
left him, the poor prisoner would have nothing to care for in this
world. I remained; but he, alas! did not. He spoke to me so sadly for
the last time, gave me a double allowance of bread and cheese parings,
kissed his finger to me, and then he was gone--gone, never to return.
I do not know his history. 'Soup of a sausage-stick!' said the jailer,
and I went to him; but I was wrong to trust in him. He took me up,
indeed, in his hand; but he put me in a cage, a treadmill. That was
hard work--jumping and jumping without getting on a bit, and only to
be laughed at.</p>

<p>"The jailer's grandchild was a pretty little fellow, with waving hair
as yellow as gold, sparkling, joyous eyes, and a laughing mouth.</p>

<p>"'Poor little mouse!' he exclaimed, peeping in at my horrid cage, and
at the same time drawing up the iron pin that closed it.</p>

<p>"I seized the opportunity, and sprang first to the window-ledge, and
thence to the conduit-pipe. Free, free! that was all I could think of,
and not the object of my journey.</p>

<p>"It became dark--it was almost night. I took up my lodgings in a
tower, where dwelt a watchman and an owl. I could not trust either of
them, and the owl least of the two. It resembles a cat, and has one
great fault--that it eats mice. But one can be on one's guard, and
that I assuredly would be. She was a respectable, extremely
well-educated old owl. She knew more than the watchman, and almost as
much as I myself did. The young owls made a great fuss about
everything.</p>

<p>"'Don't make soup of a sausage-stick,' said she.</p>

<p>"This was the severest thing she could say to them, she was so very
fond of her family. I felt so much inclined to place some reliance in
her that I cried "Pip!" from the crevice in which I was concealed. My
confidence in her seemed to please her, and she assured me that I
should be safe under her protection; that no animal would be permitted
to injure me until winter, when she might herself fall upon me, as
food would be scarce.</p>

<p>"She was very wise in all things. She proved to me that the watchman
could not blow a blast without his horn, which hung loosely about him.</p>

<p>"He piques himself exceedingly upon his performances, and fancies he
is the owl of the tower. The sound ought to be very loud, but it is
extremely weak. 'Soup of a sausage-stick!'</p>

<p>"I begged her to give me the recipe for the soup, and she explained it
to me thus:--</p>

<p>"'Soup of a sausage-stick is but a cant phrase among men, and is
differently interpreted. Every one fancies his own interpretation the
best, but in sober reality there is nothing in it whatsoever.'</p>

<p>"'Nothing!' cried I. That was a poser. 'Truth is not always pleasant,
but truth is always the best.' So also said the old owl. I considered
the matter, and came to the conclusion that when I brought _the best_
I brought more than 'soup of a sausage-stick;' and thereupon I
hastened homewards, so that I might arrive in good time to bring what
is most valuable--THE TRUTH. The mice are an enlightened community,
and their king is the cleverest of them all. He can make me his queen
for the sake of Truth."</p>

<p>"Thy truth is a falsehood," said the <character name="the last mouse">mouse</character> who had not yet had an
opportunity of speaking. "I can make the soup, and I will do it."</p>


<subheading>V.

HOW THE SOUP WAS MADE.</subheading>

<p>"I have not travelled at all," said the <character name="the last mouse">last mouse</character>. "I remained in our
own country. It is not necessary to go to foreign lands--one can
learn as well at home. I remained there. I have not acquired any
information of unnatural beings. I have not eaten information, or
conversed with owls. I confined myself to original thoughts. Will some
one now be so good as to fill the kettle with water, and put it on?
Let there be plenty of fire under it. Let the water boil--boil
briskly; then throw the sausage-stick in. Will his majesty the King of
the Mice be so condescending as to put his tail into the boiling pot,
and stir it about? The longer he stirs it, the richer the soup will
become. It costs nothing, and requires no other ingredients--it only
needs to be stirred."</p>

<p>"Cannot another do this?" asked the <character name="King of Mice">king</character>.</p>

<p>"No," said the <character name="the last mouse">mouse</character>. "The effect can only be produced by the royal
tail."</p>

<p>The water was boiled, and the <character name="King of Mice">King of the Mice</character> prepared himself for
the operation, though it was rather dangerous. He stuck his tail out,
as mice are in the habit of doing in the dairy, when they skim the
cream off the dish with their tails; but he had no sooner popped his
tail into the warm steam than he drew it out and sprang down.</p>

<p>"Of course you are my queen," said he; "but we shall wait for the soup
till our golden wedding, and the poor in my kingdom will have
something to rejoice over in the future."</p>

<p>So the nuptials were celebrated; but many of the mice, when they went
home, said, "It could not well be called soup of a sausage-stick, but
rather soup of a mouse's tail."</p>

<p>They allowed that each of the narratives was very well told, but the
whole might have been better. "I, for instance, would have related my
adventures in such and such words...."</p>

<p>These were the critics, and they are always so wise--afterwards.</p>

  <break type="section">     *       *       *       *       *</break>

<p>And this history went round the world. Opinions were divided about it,
but the historian himself remained unmoved. And this is best in great
things and in small.</p>
</body>
</text>
</xml>
